<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-10-00291</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019480</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Evolutionary biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Paleontology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Vertebrate paleontology</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Earth sciences</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Short-Snouted Toothless Ichthyosaur from China Suggests Late Triassic
                    Diversification of Suction Feeding Ichthyosaurs</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Suction Feeding Ichthyosaurs</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sander</surname>
            <given-names>P. Martin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
                        <sup>*</sup>
                    </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaohong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                        <sup>2</sup>
                    </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cheng</surname>
            <given-names>Long</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                        <sup>2</sup>
                    </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaofeng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                        <sup>2</sup>
                    </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
                <label>1</label>
                <addr-line>Steinmann Institute, Division of Palaeontology, University of Bonn, Bonn,
                    Germany</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff2">
                <label>2</label>
                <addr-line>Wuhan Institute of Geology and Mineral Resources (formerly Yichang
                    Institute of Geology and Mineral Resources), Hubei, China</addr-line>
            </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Claessens</surname>
            <given-names>Leon</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">College of the Holy Cross, United States of America</aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">martin.sander@uni-bonn.de</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: XW PMS XC LC. Performed the
                        experiments: XW PMS XC LC. Analyzed the data: PMS LC XC. Contributed
                        reagents/materials/analysis tools: XW XC LC. Wrote the paper: PMS.</p>
        </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e19480</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sander et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the
                terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
                distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and
                source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Ichthyosaurs were an important group of Mesozoic marine reptiles and existed
                        from the Early Triassic to the early Late Cretaceous. Despite a great
                        diversity in body shapes and feeding adaptations, all share greatly enlarged
                        eyes, an elongated rostrum with numerous conical teeth, and a streamlined
                        body.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methodology/Principal Findings</title>
          <p>Based on new material from China and the restudy of <italic>Shastasaurus
                            pacificus</italic>, we here reinterpret the classical large-bodied Late
                        Triassic ichthyosaur genus <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> to differ greatly
                        from the standard ichthyosaurian body plan, indicating much greater
                        morphological diversity and range of feeding adaptations in ichthyosaurs
                        than previously recognized. Phylogenetic analysis indicates a monophyletic
                        clade consisting of the giant <italic>Shonisaurus sikanniensis</italic>,
                            <italic>Guanlingsaurus liangae</italic>, and <italic>Shastasaurus
                            pacificus</italic> to which the genus name <italic>Shastasaurus</italic>
                        is applied. <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb. nov. is from the
                        Late Triassic (Carnian) Xiaowa Formation of Guizhou Province, southwestern
                        China. The species combines a diminutive head with an entirely toothless and
                        greatly reduced snout. The species also has by far the highest vertebral
                        count among ichthyosaurs (86 presacral vertebrae and &gt;110 caudal
                        vertebrae), a count that is also very high for tetrapods in general. A
                        reduced toothless snout and a diminutive head is also apparently present in
                        the giant <italic>S. sikanniensis</italic> and presumably in <italic>S.
                            pacificus</italic>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions/Significance</title>
          <p>In analogy to many modern odontocetes, <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> is
                        interpreted as a specialized suction feeder on unshelled cephalopods and
                        fish, suggesting a unique but widespread Late Triassic diversification of
                        toothless, suction-feeding ichthyosaurs. Suction feeding has not been
                        hypothesized for any of the other diverse marine reptiles of the Mesozoic
                        before, but in <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> may be linked to the Late
                        Triassic minimum in atmospheric oxygen.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Grant from Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (# 446 CHV 111/12/06) to PMS, Grant
                    from the Chinese Geolgical Survey (#1212010611603) to XFW and XCH, and funds
                    from the University of Bonn, Germany. The funders had no role in study design,
                    data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the
                    manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="10"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The Triassic witnessed an unprecedented radiation of marine reptiles, possibly
                triggered by the Permian/Triassic extinction event which left the marine environment
                largely devoid of metazoans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Benton1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Erwin1">[2]</xref> or by the dramatic decline of atmospheric oxygen level
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Huey1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Ward1">[4]</xref> during this
                period. The most successful group in this radiation were the ichthyosaurs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani2">[9]</xref> which appear in
                the fossil record in the latest Early Triassic and reached their greatest diversity
                during the Middle and Late Triassic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani1">[8]</xref>. Ichthyosaurs were very well
                adapted to the marine environment as evidenced by their worldwide record in open
                marine sediments. This invasion of the marine realm was faciliated by live birth
                which is already seen in the earliest forms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani2">[9]</xref>. Ichthyosaurs are characterized
                by their greatly enlarged eyes, elongated rostrum and numerous conical teeth.</p>
      <p>Ichthyosaurs show many evolutionary convergences with modern cetaceans <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Sander1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani1">[8]</xref>, providing
                important clues to functional versus phylogenetic constraints in whale evolution. As
                attested to by fossil stomach contents, the elongated and toothed ichthyosaur
                rostrum was used to capture fish and squid, the diet of most extant odontocetes.
                Some of these odontocetes, such as the beaked whales (Ziphiidae), some delphinids,
                pygmy and dwarf sperm whales (<italic>Kogia sima</italic> and <italic>K.
                    breviceps</italic>), and even the sperm whales (<italic>Physeter</italic>), use
                suction feeding instead of an elongate tooth-bearing rostrum to capture their prey
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Heyning1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Werth1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Werth2">[12]</xref>. In fact,
                “suction feeding is the dominant method of prey capture in aquatic
                vertebrates” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Werth1">[11, p.
                    1415]</xref> but has not been postulated for Mesozoic marine reptiles with
                the exception of the giant <italic>Shonisaurus sikanniensis</italic>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Based on new ichthyosaur finds from China, and the reexamination and reinterpretation
                of material from the western USA, we suggest that in the Late Triassic there was a
                previously unrecognized global diversification of large suction-feeding ichthyosaurs
                that probably were the ecological equivalent to the extant suction-feeding
                odontocetes.</p>
      <p>Large-bodied (adult length &gt;7 m) Late Triassic Ichthyosauria include taxa with the
                familiar elongated rostrum equipped with numerous teeth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Sander1">[6]</xref> but also a few forms lacking
                teeth combined with an abbreviated snout. These include <italic>Shastasaurus
                    liangae</italic> comb. nov. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Yin1">[14]</xref> from the early Carnian of China, <italic>Shastasaurus
                    sikanniensis</italic> comb. nov. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref> from the middle Norian of
                British Columbia, and probably <italic>Shastasaurus pacificus</italic>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Merriam1">[15]</xref> from the
                late Carnian of California.</p>
      <p>The youngest of the Chinese Triassic ichthyosaur-bearing formations is the early
                Carnian Xiaowa Formation of the Guanling area, Guizhou Province <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Wang1">[16]</xref>. The
                faunistically unique Xiaowa Formation is also known as the Wayao Formation or the
                Wayo Member of the Falang Formation in the literature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Wang1">[16]</xref>. The fossiliferous black shales
                represent the upper part of the lower member of the Xiaowa Formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Wang1">[16]</xref>. Ichthyosaurs
                belonging to three different taxa are the most common vertebrate fossils in these
                black shales, whereas fish fossils are extremely rare <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Wang1">[16]</xref>. Most common among the
                ichthyosaur taxa is the small (total length &lt;2 m) <italic>Qianichthyosaurus
                    zhoui</italic>, followed by the moderately rare and larger (total length &lt;6
                m) <italic>Guizhouichthyosaurus tangae</italic> (probable junior synonyms of this
                taxon are <italic>Cymbspondylus asiaticus</italic> and <italic>Pangjiangsaurus
                    epicharis</italic>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Wang1">[16]</xref>), and the large
                (total length &lt;9 m) <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb. nov., previously
                only known from the poorly prepared holotype of <italic>Guanlingsaurus
                    liangae</italic> housed at the Geological Survey of Guizhou Province, Guiyang,
                People's Republic of China <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Wang1">[16]</xref>. Field work by staff of the Wuhan Institute of Geology
                and Mineral Resources (the former Yichang Institute of Geology and Mineral Resources
                [YIGMR]) resulted in the aquisition of three excellent new specimens of
                this species. These and <italic>Shastasaurus pacificus</italic>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Merriam1">[15]</xref> are the focus
                of our study.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>The specimes of <italic>S. liangae</italic> comb. nov. examined first-hand for this
                study are the following three individuals: YIGMR SPCV03107, a large but incomplete
                skeleton, YIGMR SPCV03108, a complete but diagenetically flattened skeleton of a
                juvenile, and YIGMR SPCV03109, a large and complete but not yet fully prepared
                skeleton preserverd in three dimensions. In the collections of the Museum of
                Paleontology, University of California at Berkeley, USA (UCMP), the first author
                also examined the proposed neotype of <italic>Shastasaurus pacificus</italic> (UCMP
                9017) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>, a
                partial skeleton from the Carnian Hosselkus Limestone of Shasta County, California,
                USA. This find comprises the skull lacking the snout, the cervical and anterior
                dorsal vertebral column and ribs, and parts of the shoulder girdle and forelimbs
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Merriam1">[15]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The phylogenetic framework for this study was obtained through two different
                phylogenetic analyses. One is based on a modified and extended data matrix of Motani
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani3">[17]</xref> and the
                other on a modified and extended data matrix of Sander <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Sander1">[6]</xref>. The data matrices were edited
                with MacClade 4 and analyzed with PAUP 4.0b10. The matrices were modified by adding
                four new terminal taxa, <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb. nov.,
                    <italic>Guizhouichthyosaurus tangae</italic>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Yin1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Maisch2">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Shang1">[19]</xref>,
                    <italic>Shastasaurus sikanniensis</italic> comb. nov. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref>, and
                    <italic>Callawaya</italic>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls2">[20]</xref>. In
                addition, six new characters were added (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0019480.s001">Table S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0019480.s002">Table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0019480.s003">Table S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0019480.s004">Table S4</xref>). <italic>Shastasaurus
                    pacificus</italic> was recoded in the matrices based on personal inspection by
                P.M.S. in 2007 to only include the material from the late Carnian Hosselkuss
                Limestone of California <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Merriam1">[15]</xref> for reasons explained below. The modified matrix based on
                Motani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani3">[17]</xref> has 36
                taxa and 111 characters, and that based on Sander <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Sander1">[6]</xref> has 15 taxa (the
                Neoichthyosauria being treated as single terminal taxon) and 125 characters. The
                search mode was heuristic and employed exactly the same settings as in the original
                analyses. The resulting trees were optimized both under DELTRAN and ACCTRAN
                character optimization, but only unambiguous character state transformations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0019480.s005">Table S5</xref>) were
                used for inferences about character evolution.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>Systematic Paleontology</title>
        <p>Ichthyosauria Blainville, 1835</p>
        <p>Merriamosauria Motani, 1999</p>
        <p><italic>Shastasaurus</italic> Merriam, 1895</p>
        <sec id="s3a1">
          <title>Type species</title>
          <p><italic>Shastasaurus pacificus</italic> Merriam, 1895</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a2">
          <title>Included species</title>
          <p><italic>Shastasaurus sikanniensis</italic> comb. nov. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref>, <italic>Shastasaurus
                            liangae</italic> comb. nov. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Yin1">[14]</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a3">
          <title>Revised diagnosis based on the phylogenetic analysis</title>
          <p>Large to gigantic Shastasauridae diagnosed by the following unambiguous and
                        unequivocal synapomorphies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0019480.s005">Table S5</xref>): abbreviated rostrum and
                        extremely slender lower jaw. Unambiguous but equivocal (i.e. consistency
                        index is &lt;1) synapomorphies are the lack of a parietal ridge and the loss
                        of marginal teeth. Three ambiguous and equivocal synapomorphies are listed
                        in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0019480.s005">Table
                            S5</xref>. <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> differs from all other
                        ichthyosaurs in the reduced snout and lack of teeth. In addition,
                            <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> differs from other basal Merriamosauria
                        except for <italic>Shonisaurus popularis</italic> and
                            <italic>Besanosaurus</italic> in its larger size.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a4">
          <title>Remarks</title>
          <p>The character state “loss of marginal teeth” is also unambiguous
                        and unequivocal if <italic>Hupehsuchus</italic>, which is not an ichthyosaur
                            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani1">[8]</xref>, is deleted from the
                        analysis. While the holotype of the type species <italic>S.
                            pacificus</italic> is incompletely preserved, it shows at least one of
                        the synapomorphies of the genus <italic>Shastasaurus</italic>, the slender
                        lower jaw. Character optimization indicates that both the lack of teeth and
                        the reduced snout must have been present in <italic>S. pacificus</italic>
                        despite them not being preserved.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a5">
          <title>Horizon and localities</title>
          <p>Upper Triassic, lower Carnian to middle Norian of southwestern China and
                        western North America (California and British Columbia).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a6">
          <title><italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb. nov</title>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a7">
          <title>Synonymy</title>
          <p><italic>Guanlingsaurus liangae</italic> (Yin in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Yin1">[14]</xref>)</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a8">
          <title>Holotype</title>
          <p>Geological Survey of Guizhou Province, Guiyang, People's Republic of
                        China specimen GMR 014, a complete skeleton. However, there are doubts about
                        the integrity of the material. The specimen was briefly described and
                        figured by Yin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Yin1">[14]</xref> as <italic>Guanlingsaurus liangae</italic> and
                        access is limited <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Wang1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Maisch2">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Shang1">[19]</xref>. However, autapomorphies of the species such as
                        the very high number of presacral and caudal vertebrae are clearly
                        discernable from the publication of Yin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Yin1">[14]</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a9">
          <title>Referred material</title>
          <p>YIGMR SPCV03107, YIGMR SPCV03108, and YIGMR SPCV03109.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a10">
          <title>Horizon and locality</title>
          <p>Upper Triassic, lower Carnian laminated beds of the lower Xiaowa Formation,
                        Guanling County, Guizhou Provice, southwestern China <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Yin1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Wang1">[16]</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3a11">
          <title>Revised diagnosis based on the phylogenetic analysis</title>
          <p>Large <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> with a very small skull, less than
                        10% of total length. <italic>S. liangae</italic> comb. nov. is
                        diagnosed by the following unambiguous but equivocal synapomorphies:
                        postorbital triradiate in shape and contiguous shaft of ulna absent. Other
                        characters are that the rostrum is greatly reduced in length, mainly
                        resulting from very short and slender premaxillae and dentaries. The nasals
                        and the angulars of the lower jaw reach the tip of the snout. The jaws are
                        completely toothless. There are 86 presacral and &gt;110 caudal vertebrae,
                        the highest number of any ichthyosaur <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Maisch1">[7]</xref>.
                            <italic>S. liangae</italic> comb. nov. differs from <italic>Shastasaurus
                            sikanniensis</italic> comb. nov. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref> in the lacrimal
                        having numerous small to medium-sized nutritive foramina, the supratemporal
                        extending well posterior of the parietal, and in a more strongly
                        foreshortened propodium and zeugopodium in both the forelimb and the
                        hindlimb. <italic>S. liangae</italic> comb. nov. differs from <italic>S.
                            sikanniensis</italic> comb. nov. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref> and <italic>S.
                            pacificus</italic>
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>,
                            <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Merriam1">[15]</xref>
                        in the lack of a preaxial notch in the radiale. Differs from <italic>S.
                            pacificus</italic> in the relative longer postorbital region and larger
                        upper temporal openings, the long axes of which are nearly parallel in
                            <italic>S. liangae</italic> but enclose an angle of about 60° in
                            <italic>S. pacificus</italic> because of its posteriorly diverging
                        parietals.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>Description of <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb. nov</title>
        <p>The largest skeleton of <italic>S. liangae</italic> (YIGMR SPCV03109) is 8.3 m
                    long. This is somewhat longer than the holotype and slightly longer than the
                    three-dimensionally preserved specimen YGMIR SPCV03107 which must have been
                    about 7 m in total length. The juvenile (YIGMR SPCV03108, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019480-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) is 3.74 m long. Skull length as
                    measured along skull midline is 8.3% of total length in the largest
                    specimen and 9.3% in the juvenile. Skull length is 17.7% of
                    presacral lenght in the juvenile compared to &gt;40% in most other
                    ichthyosaurs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Sander1">[6]</xref>. The most striking feature about the skull of
                        <italic>S. liangae</italic> comb. nov. is its very short snout region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019480-g002">Figs. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019480-g003">3</xref>). In addition, the snout is completely
                    toothless, as best shown by the juvenile skull because of the partial
                    disarticulation of its jaw bones. There is no evidence for a dental groove in
                    the dentary, premaxilla, and maxilla. All bones contributing to the snout taper
                    rapidly to a point. The premaxilla is dominated by an elongate foramen that
                    enters the bone obliquely in posterior direction. Likewise, the maxilla shows
                    several very large foramina that take up much of the lateral side of the bone
                    and are not seen in any other ichthyosaur. The maxilla is excluded from the
                    external nares by the premaxilla and lacrimal. There is a very large internasal
                    foramen between the external nares. The lacrimal is perforated by numerous small
                    to medium-sized foramina. Uniquely among ichthyosaurs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>, and extremely unusual
                    among sauropsids, the nasal extends anteriorly to the very tip of the snout
                        (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019480-g002">Fig. 2C, D</xref>). The orbit
                    is evenly oval in outline, and the orbital and postorbital region of the skull
                    are as in other Merriamosauria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0019480-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title><italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb. nov.</title>
            <p>Juvenile individual YGMIR SPCV03108, total length 3.75 m. Scale bar, 50
                            cm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="pone-0019480-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Skull anatomy of <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb.
                            nov.</title>
            <p>Photograph and drawing of skull of YGMIR SPCV03107. (A) in left lateral
                            view. Note the greatly abbreviated rostrum, the complete lack of teeth,
                            the large foramina in the maxillary and lacrimal bones, and the dorsally
                            convex coronoid region of the dentary (arrow). (B) in dorsal view. Note
                            the nasals extending to the tip of the rostrum. Abbreviations: a,
                            angular; ar, articular; d, dentary; en, external nares; f, frontal; if,
                            internasal foramen; j, jugal; l, lacrimal; mx, maxilla; pa, parietal;
                            pf, postfrontal; pm, premaxilla; po, postorbital; prf, prefrontal; qj,
                            quadratojugal; sa, surangular; sq, squamosal; st, supratemporal; uto,
                            upper temporal opening.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The dentaries of the lower jaw are very short and completely edentulous with a
                    smooth dorsal surface. In lateral view, there is a marked dorsal convexity in
                    the coronoid region of the dentary opposite the maxilla, which is ventrally
                    concave. Just as unusual as the nasal extending to tip of the upper jaw is the
                    configuration of the angular that ventrally, together with the splenial, extends
                    to the very tip of the lower jaw, as can be seen in the skull YIGMR SPCV03109 in
                    ventral view and in the juvenile YIGMR SPCV03108 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019480-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). The postdentary region of the lower
                    jaw is as in other Merriamosauria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref> and ends in a large
                    retroarticular process. The hyoid bones are only observable in the juvenile and
                    are remarkably long, reaching 31% of the length of the lower jaw.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0019480-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Skull anatomy of <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb.
                            nov.</title>
            <p>Photograph (A) and drawing (B) of the skull of the juvenile specimen
                            YGMIR SPCV03108. Crushing lead to both the dorsal and the right lateral
                            view being exposed. Note the greatly abbreviated rostrum, the complete
                            lack of teeth, and the large foramina in the maxilla. Also note the
                            nasals extending to the tip of the rostrum and the angular almost
                            extending to the tip of the lower jaw. The extent of the left hyoid bone
                            is highlighted by the arrows. Abbreviations: a, angular; d, dentary; f,
                            frontal; hy, hyoid bone: j, jugal; l, lacrimal; mx, maxilla; pa,
                            parietal; pf, postfrontal; pm, premaxilla; po, postorbital; prf,
                            prefrontal; q, quadrate; sa, surangular; sq, squamosal; st,
                            supratemporal.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p><italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb. nov. has by far the highest number of
                    vertebrae of any ichthyosaur <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Sander1">[6]</xref> with approximately 86 presacrals and over 100 caudal
                    vertebrae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019480-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). This is
                    also among the highest numbers in amniotes in general <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Mller1">[21]</xref>. From the first cervical to
                    the middle dorsal, the vertebrae nearly double in height and width. Compared to
                    other Merriamosauria, the loss of contact of the diapophysis with the neural
                    arch occurs very far back, on the 69th presacral. Despite the very high number
                    of vertebrae, the body shape index <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref> of 3.9 is similar to
                    other long-bodied Triassic Merriamosauria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref>. The caudal vertebral
                    column is very straight without a tailbend (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019480-g001">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
        <p>The appendicular skeleton is generally similar to that of other basal
                    Merriamosauria, with the proximal bones of the anterior limbs all being
                    disc-shaped, suggesting that they were surrounded by extensive cartilage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019480-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). Distally, the
                    forefins appear to have been incompletely ossified as well, considering that all
                    three new specimens preserve very few fin bones except for humerus, radius, ulna
                    and radiale. This suggests that the distal carpals, metacarpals, and phalanges
                    possibly were not ossified at all. The alternative explanation, that they were
                    lost taphonomically, is inconsistent with the high degree of articulation
                    generally observed in marine reptiles from the Xiaowa Formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Wang1">[16]</xref>. If these
                    elements were ossified, it appears likely that at least one out of three
                    specimens should have preserved some of these bones. The incomplete ossification
                    of the distal forelimbs is also suggested by the illustration of the holotype
                    with only three digits preserved and an apparent phalangeal formula of 1-1-0
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Yin1">[14, plate
                    9]</xref>. The humerus of <italic>S. liangae</italic> is wider than long,
                    and its length is only 1% of the body length. Together with the small
                    zeugopodium of the forelimb and the poor ossification of the distal limb, this
                    suggests that the forefins were disproportionally small in life. The hind fins
                    appear to have been even smaller than the forefins, and the humerus to femur
                    ratio is 1.16. However, the proximal bones of the hindfins retain a shaft and
                    are remarkably stout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019480-g004">Fig.
                        4B</xref>). The hindfins also appear poorly ossified distally.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0019480-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Appendicular skeleton of <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb.
                            nov.</title>
            <p>(A) Pectoral girdle and forelimb elements of YGMIR SPCV03107. (B) Pelvic
                            girdle and hindlimb elements of YGMIR SPCV03107. Abbreviations: f,
                            femur; fi, fibula; h, humerus; i, ischium; r, radius; s, scapula; t,
                            tibia; u, ulna. Scale bars, 10 cm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.g004" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>Reevaluation of <italic>Shastasaurus pacificus</italic></title>
        <p><italic>Shastasaurus pacificus</italic> was the first large ichthyosaur from the
                    Triassic for which articulated material became known. It was first described
                    over a century ago based on a specimen from the late Carnian of northern
                    California <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Merriam1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Merriam2">[22]</xref>. Although the rostrum remains unknown, being broken
                    off in the only reasonably complete skull, UCMP 9017 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019480-g005">Fig. 5</xref>), the preserved parts of maxilla and
                    dentary in this skull are toothless <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Maisch3">[23]</xref>. Notwithstanding,
                        <italic>Shastasaurus pacificus</italic> was reconstructed several times in
                    the past to conform to the general ichthyosaurian skull shape with a long
                    rostrum and numerous teeth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Maisch1">[e.g.]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani3">[ 7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Maisch3">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Callaway1">[23,24]</xref>. These reconstructions were apparently inspired by
                    the putative assignment of a normal ichthyosaurian snout fragment from the Upper
                    Triassic of Mexico to <italic>Shastasaurus altispinus</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls2">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Callaway1">[24]</xref> and on
                    the assignment of a long-snouted ichthyosaur from the Norian of British Columbia
                    to <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> as <italic>S. neoscapularis</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan2">[25]</xref>. However
                    this material has since been placed in its own genus,
                        <italic>Callawayia</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Maisch1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls2">[20]</xref>. We
                    follow the view of Nicholls &amp; Manabe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls2">[20]</xref> that the genus
                        <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> should be restriced to Merriam's <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Merriam1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Merriam3">[26]</xref> original
                    type series from the Hosselkus Limestone of California. The notion of
                        <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> being a typical, long-snouted ichthyosaur is
                    also reflected in the recent reassignment by Shang &amp; Li <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Shang1">[19]</xref> of
                        <italic>Guizhouichthyosaurus tangae</italic> to the genus
                        <italic>Shastasaurus</italic>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0019480-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Partial skull of <italic>Shastasaurus pacificus</italic> (UCMP 9017)
                            from the Late Triassic of California, USA, in (A) lateral, (B) dorsal,
                            and (C) anterolateral view.</title>
            <p>Based on this skull, <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> has repeatedly been
                            reconstructed with a long, tooth-bearing rostrum. However, note the
                            slenderness of the lower jaw (B, C) and the strong anterior taper of the
                            snout (B), both of which are more consistent with the abbreviated and
                            toothless snout of <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb. nov. than
                            with the traditional long-snouted reconstruction of this skull (as,
                            e.g., in references <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Merriam2">[22]</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Maisch3">[23]</xref>).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.g005" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Re-examination of UCMP 9017 in light of the new Chinese material and character
                    optimization based on phylogenetic analysis and suggests that <italic>S.
                        pacificus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019480-g005">Fig.
                        5</xref>) had the same reduced snout as <italic>Shastasaurus
                        liangae</italic> comb. nov. In addition, among the material from California,
                    distal limb elements are rare and not preserved in articulation, and isolated
                    teeth were never found with any of the Californian <italic>Shastasaurus</italic>
                    material <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Merriam1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Merriam2">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Merriam3">[26]</xref>. These observations are consistent with the
                    edentulous condition and reduced distal fins of <italic>Shastasaurus
                        liangae</italic> comb. nov. However, some anatomical differences, such as
                    the relatively longer postorbital region, the larger upper temporal openings,
                    and the posteriorly diverging parietals indicate that <italic>Shastasaurus
                        liangae</italic> is not a junior synonym of <italic>Shastasaurus
                        pacificus</italic> (see diagnosis).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>Phylogenetic relationships and taxonomic consequences</title>
        <p>A very similar tree topology resulted from both phylogenetic analyses, one based
                    on a modified and extended data matrix of Motani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani3">[17]</xref> and one based on a modified
                    and extended data matrix of Sander <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Sander1">[6]</xref>. In this article, we will
                    discuss the analysis of the modified matrix of Motani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani3">[17]</xref> in detail because it
                    represents the most widely used data set in ichthyosaur phylogenetic research.
                    Our analysis based on the modified and extended data matrix of Motani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani3">[17]</xref> recovered
                    72 most parsimonious trees (MPTs). The strict consensus of these (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019480-g006">Fig. 6</xref>) had a length of 254
                    steps, a consistency index of 0.569, a rescaled consistency index of 0.462, and
                    a retention index of 0.81. The disagreement between the MPTs is largely confined
                    to the outgroup taxa and the basal Merriamosauria. Exept for these poorly
                    resolved areas and the new taxa, the topology of the tree does not differ from
                    that found in the earlier analysis by Motani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani3">[17]</xref>. The quality metrics of our
                    analysis do not differ much from that of Motani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani3">[17]</xref> either, which had a
                    consistency index of 0.654 and was one step shorter. The sligthly poorer
                    measures for the tree statistics in our analysis are not surprising because of
                    the addition of four terminal taxa and of new characters. However, we note that
                    the scope of the current study is not a reanalysis of ichthyosaurian
                    interrelationships but the determination of the phylogenetic position of
                        <italic>S. liangae</italic>.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0019480-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Phylogenetic relationships of <italic>Shastasaurus</italic>.</title>
            <p>This cladogram represents the strict consensus of 72 most parsimonious
                            trees. Differences in topology among MPTs are mainly found among the
                            outgroup taxa and the basal Merriamosauria. Derived Parvipelvia were
                            part of the analysis but were omitted for clarity. Relevant nodes are
                            numbered in accordance with <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0019480.s005">Table S5</xref>. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref> section and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s5">Supporting Information</xref> for details of
                            analysis.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.g006" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In the analysis of the modified matrix of Motani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani3">[17]</xref>, <italic>Shastasaurus
                        liangae</italic> comb. nov. is most closely related to <italic>Shastasaurus
                        pacificus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019480-g006">Fig.
                        6</xref>). These two taxa in turn are most closely related to
                        <italic>Shonisaurus sikanniensis</italic>, forming a monophyletic group.
                        <italic>Shonisaurus popularis</italic> was found to be less derived than
                    this clade, making the genus <italic>Shonisaurus</italic> paraphyletic. This
                    leads us to propose including <italic>S. sikanniensis</italic> in the genus
                        <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> as <italic>Shastasaurus sikanniensis</italic>
                    comb. nov. We feel justified in doing so because the original authors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref> had
                    already noted the strong affinites of this species with
                        <italic>Shastasaurus</italic>, and their decision to assign <italic>S.
                        sikanniensis</italic> to <italic>Shonisauris</italic> was not based on a
                    phylogenetic analysis.</p>
        <p>We used the unambiguous and unequivocal synapomorphies at node 57 (abbreviated
                    rostrum and slender lower jaw, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0019480.s005">Table S5</xref>) to diagnose
                        <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> because of the major morphological departure
                    from all other ichthyosaurs they represent. Retaining the original genus names
                    for <italic>S. sikanniensis</italic> and <italic>S. liangae</italic> was not an
                    option because of the resulting paraphyly of the genus
                        <italic>Shonisaurus</italic>. Since the genus name
                        <italic>Shonisaurus</italic> has to stay with the type species <italic>S.
                        popularis</italic>, the only taxonomic options for <italic>S.
                        sikanniensis</italic> were either to erect a new genus name or to include it
                    and <italic>G. liangae</italic> in the genus <italic>Shastasaurus</italic>. The
                    list of apomorphies for <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> and the three included
                    species are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0019480.s005">Table S5</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Toothlessness in ichthyosaurs</title>
        <p>Previously, complete toothlessness had only been described for the adults of one
                    other Triassic ichthyosaur species, i.e., the giant <italic>Shastasaurus
                        sikanniensis</italic> comb. nov. However, the juveniles of the <italic>S.
                        sikanniensis</italic> appear to have had teeth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref>. Additionally, Nicholls
                    &amp; Manabe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref> suggested that <italic>Shonisaurus popularis</italic>
                    also lacked teeth in the adult, but this is difficult to verify because of the
                    poor preservation of the material.</p>
        <p><italic>S. sikanniensis</italic> comb. nov. resembles <italic>S. liangae</italic>
                    comb. nov. in its toothlessness, in that its snout is reduced, the hyoids are
                    enlarged, and at &lt;3 m <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref>, the skull is small relative to the estimated body
                    length of 21 m. Our phylogenetic analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0019480-g006">Fig. 6</xref>) indicates that the Shastasauridae
                    evolved towards tooth reduction and loss, possibly beginning with
                        <italic>Besanosaurus leptorhynchus</italic> which has few and very small
                    teeth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-DalSasso1">[27]</xref>.
                    The short snout of <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb. nov. thus may
                    have evolved from a long-snouted ichthyosaur with a slender rostrum like
                        <italic>Besanosaurus</italic> by strong heterochrony. We hypothesize that
                    early developmental stages of this ancestor that were retained by
                        <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb. nov. are the failure of teeth to
                    form, the participation of the nasal and angular in the tip of the snout, and
                    the very large internasal foramen. In embryos of extant Reptilia, the jaws
                    ossify well before the development of teeth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-DeBeer1">[28]</xref>. Similarly, at least in
                        <italic>Lacerta</italic> and <italic>Sphenodon</italic> embryos, the
                    premaxillary bones are separated among the skull midline by the nasals which
                    reach the tip of the snout <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-DeBeer1">[28]</xref>. The fairly late-stage embryos of the sauropodomorph
                    dinosaur <italic>Massospondylus</italic> are toothless as well <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Reisz1">[29]</xref>, but early
                    hatchlings have a full complement of teeth. The alternative hypothesis to
                    explain the evolution of toothlessness in <italic>Shastasaurus</italic>, early
                    senescence of the dental lamina, would require senescence to have occurred in
                    early juveniles, requiring a much greater shift in development than the first
                    hypothesis.</p>
        <p>Although toothlessness occurs in mature individuals of a few Jurassic ichthyosaur
                    species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>,
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref>,
                    the toothless condition in some of these is a taphonomic artifact because of the
                    loose, aulacodont tooth implantation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>. None of the Jurassic forms
                    has a smooth dorsal surface of the dentary without a trace of a dental groove or
                    tooth sockets <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>, and none has the strikingly reduced snout of
                        <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb. nov., which only accounts for
                    42% of lower jaw length (the snout ratio of McGowan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan3">[30]</xref>), as compared to
                    53% in the Jurasssic ichthyosaur with the shortest snout,
                        <italic>Ichthyosaurus breviceps</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan3">[30]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Modern analog</title>
        <p>The closest modern analogs in skull shape, body proportions and body size to
                        <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> and the lesser known other two species
                    of <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> are the unusual Ziphiidae (beaked whales,
                    Odontoceti <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Clarke1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nowak1">[32]</xref>) which range from 6 m to 11 m in length and have a
                    proportionally small skull and a snout that is toothless, save for one or two
                    pairs of peculiar teeth in the lower jaw, which do not erupt in the females of
                    some species. In addition, ziphiids share with <italic>Shastasaurus
                        liangae</italic> an elongate body and very small forefins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Clarke1">[31]</xref>. As in
                        <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> species, their toothlessness evolved from
                    ancestral forms with numerous teeth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Werth1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Lambert1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Lambert2">[34]</xref>. Further similarities in
                    the skull of <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> and ziphiid whales are the
                    dorsally convex coronoid region of the lower jaw and the enlarged hyoids. Other
                    modern odontocetes tending towards toothlessness are the modern sperm whales
                        (<italic>Physeter</italic> and the pygmy and dwarf sperm whales,
                        <italic>Kogia sima</italic> and <italic>K. breviceps</italic>), some
                    delphinids such as Risso's dolphin (<italic>Grampus griseus</italic>, a few
                    lower teeth and no upper teeth), and the narwhal (<italic>Monodon
                        monoceros</italic>) which only retains its huge maxillary tusk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nowak1">[32]</xref>. Among
                    these, <italic>Kogia</italic> spp., <italic>Grampus</italic>, and
                        <italic>Monodon</italic> have an abbreviated rostrum as seen in
                        <italic>Shastasaurus</italic>.</p>
        <p>These odontocete taxa and the ziphiid whales are suction feeders in which the
                    tongue is pulled back rapidly by strong retractor muscles that are attached to
                    hypertrophied hyoid bones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Heyning1">[10]</xref>. In this way, prey items are taken up by the negative
                    pressure generated in the oral cavity, obviating the need for teeth to hold them
                    before swallowing. Based on the morphological similarity of suction-feeding
                    odontocete whales and <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb. nov.,
                    including the enlarged hyoids and the massive convex coronoid region of the
                    lower jaw, and by exclusion of other options, we suggest that <italic>S.
                        liangae</italic> comb. nov., and probably <italic>S. pacificus</italic> and
                        <italic>S. sikanniensis</italic> comb. nov., were specialized in a similar
                    manner (see also Nichols &amp; Manabe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref> on <italic>S.
                        sikanniensis</italic>). An importantant component of the diet of most
                    suction-feeding odontocetes, particulary of ziphiids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Clarke1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-MacLeod1">[35]</xref>, are coleoid cephalopods.
                    Cephalopods, which are commonly bioluminescent, would have been suitable prey
                    for visually hunting ichthyosaurs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Massare1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani4">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Massare2">[38]</xref> as well, especially since
                    bioluminescent cephalopods would have been visually detectable below the photic
                    zone and at night. The eyes of <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> species appear to
                    be average-sized for ichthyosaurs, although this is difficult to quantify
                    because of lack of comparative size standards. They were clearly relatively
                    larger than in <italic>Cymbospondylus</italic> but smaller than in mixosaurs and
                        <italic>Qianichthyosaurus</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Sander1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls3">[39]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Werth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Werth1">[11]</xref>
                    established the relationship between an abbreviated snout and generation of
                    suction in modern cetaceans but, as the example of the ziphiids shows, an
                    abbreviated rostrum is not a requirement for suction feeding. The specific
                    mechanism of suction feeding in <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> probably was
                    different from that of ziphiid and other whales, because the latter have a
                    secondary soft palate that aids in generating negative pressure. The exact
                    mechanism of suction generation is difficult to infer in
                        <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> but may have involved specialized soft tissue
                    structures in the snout such as lips or cheeks that would have tightly closed
                    the mouth on the sides and increased the efficency of suction. The potential
                    presence of such structures is hinted at by the unique large foramina in the
                    maxillary and lacimal bones of <italic>S. liangae</italic> comb. nov. The
                    massive retroarticular process of the lower jaw, combined with the reduced
                    rostrum, may also have played a role in suction feeding because they would have
                    allowed very fast and forceful opening of the jaws. Preferred prey of
                        <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> may have been pelagic coleoid cephalopods and
                    fish. Both of these are fast swimmers, making suction feeding a more efficient
                    hunting mechanism than the elongated, tooth-bearing rostrum plesiomorphic for
                    ichthyosaurs in general and Merriamosauria in particular. Shelled cephalopods,
                    predominantly ammonites, are slower swimmers and occur abundantly together with
                        <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> but may have been less attractive prey for
                        <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> because of their protective shell and rounded
                    shape.</p>
        <p>As noted, further similarities of <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> and Ziphiidae are
                    the very small pectoral fins and the slender, elongate body. In ziphiids, the
                    reduced pectoral fins are believed to be an adaptation to deep diving, reducing
                    drag on the descent. The functional significance of body elongation and high
                    vertebral number in <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb. nov. is not
                    clear. High vertebral numbers are typical of marine reptiles <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Mller1">[21]</xref>, and
                        <italic>S. liangae</italic> comb. nov. appears to be the culmination of this
                    evolutionary trend among ichthyosaurs.</p>
        <p>Notably, just like the modern suction-feeding odontocetes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nowak1">[32]</xref>, the species of
                        <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> show a size range from about 4 m to about 20 m
                    adult body length. This similar size bracket may have biomechanical reasons
                    rooted in the scaling of muscle power and maneuverability. Whales larger than 20
                    m (exclusively mysticetes) are filter feeders, whereas a body size &lt;4 m, seen
                    in most dolphins and toothed ichthyosaurs, may favor catching prey with a long
                    slender rostrum studded with teeth.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Diversification of suction feeding ichthyosaurs</title>
        <p>Our detailed study of the osteology of the <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic>
                    comb. nov. and the phylogenetic analysis of related taxa reveals a Late Triassic
                    diversification of large, toothless, suction-feeding ichthyosaurs. The spatial
                    and temporal distribution of the species of <italic>Shastasaurus</italic>
                    indicates that this diversification was widespread, if not global, and
                    long-lasting, from at least the early Carnian to the middle Norian. Considering
                    the only recently recognized <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Brayard1">[40]</xref> very long duration of the Late Triassic, especially
                    the Norian, the diversification of suction feeding ichthyosaurs thus may have
                    lasted for up to 32 million years and may represent a hidden radiation in the
                    Triassic oceans, only incompletely captured by the fossil record.</p>
        <p>Support for this view comes from the small number, low diversity, and limited
                    geographic spread of Late Triassic ichthyosaur localities compared to those of
                    Middle Triassic age <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-McGowan1">[5]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani1">[8]</xref>, especially considering the vastly longer duration of
                    the Late Triassic compared to the Middle Triassic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Brayard1">[40]</xref>. Add to this the
                    apparently pelagic lifestyle of <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> and a similar
                    picture emerges as for the ziphiid whale fossil record. Because of their pelagic
                    life style and deep-diving habit, these whales are not only very rare in fossil
                    whale faunas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Lambert1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Lambert2">[34]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Bianucci1">[41]</xref> but are also the least known group of whales today. A
                    pelagic lifestyle for <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> is suggested by its rarity
                    in the Xiaowa Formation of China and the Hosselkus Limestone of California and
                    also by the observation that all of the beds that yielded
                        <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> have a pelagic depositional environment as
                    well as a distinctly pelagic fauna of ammonites, halobiid bivalves and
                    vertebrates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Wang1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Merriam2">[22]</xref>),</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Suction feeding and low atmospheric oxygen</title>
        <p>Restudy of <italic>Shastasaurus liangae</italic> comb. nov. from China and
                        <italic>Shastasaurus pacificus</italic> from the United States adds another,
                    unexpected type to the already very diverse feeding adaptations in Triassic
                    ichthyosaurs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Massare1">[36]</xref> and reveals a Late Triassic diversification of large
                    to giant toothless, presumably suction-feeding ichthyosaurs. By the Late
                    Triassic, ichthyosaurs had evolved the widest range of trophic adaptations known
                    in any marine tetrapod group <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Sander1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Massare1">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani5">[42]</xref>. The diversification of ichthyosaurs in the Early and
                    Middle Triassic happened together with the recovery of marine invertebrate life
                    from the devastating end-Permian extinction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Benton1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Erwin1">[2]</xref>. In particular, ammonites
                    apparently recovered much more quickly than the benthic invertebrates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Brayard1">[40]</xref>. If this
                    is indicative of a fast recovery of cephalopods in general, it would explain the
                    rapid radiation of early ichthyosaurs, because shell-less cephalopods were the
                    main prey of ichthyosaurs. Apart from the diversity of standard ichthyosaurs
                    (cephalopod and fish eaters with an isodont dentition of small conical teeth)
                    and the putative suction feeders described here, the Triassic witnessed the
                    evolution of ichthyosaurs belonging to other feeding guilds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Massare1">[36]</xref>. These
                    include forms with crushing dentitions (<italic>Phalarodon</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Schmitz1">[43]</xref>,
                        <italic>Tholodus</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Sander2">[44]</xref>,
                        <italic>Xinminosaurus</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Jiang1">[45]</xref>) and, in
                    the Norian, a large marine top predator (<italic>Himalayasaurus</italic>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani6">[46]</xref>). The
                    appearance of <italic>S. liangae</italic> comb. nov. in the poorly oxygenated
                    environment of the Carnian Xiaowa Formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Wang1">[16]</xref> and the diversification of
                    suction-feeding ichthyosaurs is consistent with the Phanerozoic minimum in
                    atmospheric oxygen in the Late Triassic, which may have given air-breathing
                    marine reptiles and low oxygen-tolerant cephalopods a competitive advantage over
                    gill-breathing fish <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Ward1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Wang1">[16]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Suction-feeding ichthyosaurs of the genus <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> did not
                    survive into the Jurassic. This may have been because they lost their
                    competitive advantage as atmospheric oxygen rose again, although there are no
                    other large suction feeders known among Early Jurassic marine vertebrate.
                    Alternatively, suction-feeding ichthyosaurs may have fallen victim to the
                    end-Triassic extinction event that greatly reduced ichthyosaur taxonomic and
                    ecological diversity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Sander1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani5">[42]</xref>, with only the thunniform longirostrine
                    Neoichthyosauria surviving. These radiated throughout the Jurassic but never
                    reached the trophic diversity of Triassic forms again, including the
                    suction-feeding <italic>Shastasaurus</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0019480.s001" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The additional characters in the modified and extended character matrix from
                        Motani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani3">[17]</xref>.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0019480.s002" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Characters states in the four new terminal taxa in the modified and extended
                        character matrix from Motani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani3">[17]</xref>.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0019480.s003" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Coding of the six new characters for all taxa of the modified and extended
                        character matrix from Motani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani3">[17]</xref>.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0019480.s004" mimetype="text/plain" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.s004" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>NEXUS file of the modified and extended character matrix from Motani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani3">[17]</xref> used in
                        the phylogenetic analysis.</p>
          <p>(TXT)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0019480.s005" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0019480.s005" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>List of apomorphies found in the phylogenetic analysis based on the modified
                        matrix from Motani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0019480-Motani3">[17]</xref>. ACCTRAN = optimization
                        criterion accelerated transformation,
                        DELTRAN = optimization criterion delayed
                        transformation. Bold print indicates unambiguous and unequivocal
                        synapomorphies.</p>
          <p>(DOC)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Philip Gingerich, Jes Rust, and Olivier Lambert for discussions on ziphiid
                whales, Z.-Q. Zhao for preparation, and G. Oleschinski for help with photography.
                The manuscript benefitted greatly from formal reviews by Olivier Lambert, Judy
                Massare, and Erin Maxwell.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Benton1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <source>When Life Nearly Died. The Greatest Mass Extinction of All Time</source>
                    <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Thames &amp; Hudson.</publisher-name>
                    <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">336</size>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Erwin1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <source>Extinction. How Life on Earth Nearly Ended 250 Million Years
                        Ago</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Princeton University Press.</publisher-name>
                    <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">296</size>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Huey1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Hypoxia, global warming, and terrestrial Late Permian
                        extinctions.</article-title>
                    <source>Science</source>
                    <volume>308</volume>
                    <fpage>398</fpage>
                    <lpage>401</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Ward1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <source>Out of Thin Air. Dinosaurs, Birds, and Earth's Ancient
                        Atmosphere</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Joseph Henry Publishers.</publisher-name>
                    <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">296</size>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-McGowan1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGowan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Motani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Handbook of Palaeoherpetology. Part 8.</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sues</surname><given-names>H-D</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <publisher-loc>Munich</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Dr. Friedrich Pfeil Verlag.</publisher-name>
                    <comment>Ichthyopterygia:</comment>
                    <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">175</size>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Sander1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Ichthyosauria: their diversity, distribution, and
                        phylogeny.</article-title>
                    <source>Paläontologische Zeitschrift</source>
                    <volume>74</volume>
                    <fpage>1</fpage>
                    <lpage>35</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Maisch1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maisch</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matzke</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>The Ichthyosauria.</article-title>
                    <source>Stuttgarter Beiträge zur Naturkunde B</source>
                    <volume>298</volume>
                    <fpage>1</fpage>
                    <lpage>159</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Motani1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Motani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>The evolution of marine reptiles.</article-title>
                    <source>Evolution: Education and Outreach</source>
                    <volume>2</volume>
                    <fpage>224</fpage>
                    <lpage>235</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Motani2">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Motani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <article-title>Warm-blooded “sea dragons”?</article-title>
                    <source>Science</source>
                    <volume>328</volume>
                    <fpage>1361</fpage>
                    <lpage>1362</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Heyning1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heyning</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title>Suction feeding in beaked whales: morphological and observational
                        evidence.</article-title>
                    <source>Natural History Museum <italic>of</italic> Los Angeles County
                        Contribution <italic>in</italic> Science</source>
                    <volume>464</volume>
                    <fpage>1</fpage>
                    <lpage>12</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Werth1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Werth</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Mandibular and dental variation and the evolution of suction
                        feeding in Odontoceti.</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of Mammalogy</source>
                    <volume>87</volume>
                    <fpage>579</fpage>
                    <lpage>588</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Werth2">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Werth</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Functional morphology of the sperm whale tongue, with reference
                        to suction feeding.</article-title>
                    <source>Aquatic Mammals</source>
                    <volume>30</volume>
                    <fpage>405</fpage>
                    <lpage>418</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Nicholls1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholls</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Giant ichthyosaurs of the Triassic-A new species of
                            <italic>Shonisaurus</italic> from the Pardonet Formation (Norian, Late
                        Triassic) of British Columbia.</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology</source>
                    <volume>24</volume>
                    <fpage>838</fpage>
                    <lpage>849</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Yin1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>A preliminary study on the early Late Triassic reptiles from
                        Guanling, Guizhou, China (in Chinese).</article-title>
                    <source>Geology-Geochemistry</source>
                    <volume>28</volume>
                    <fpage>1</fpage>
                    <lpage>23</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Merriam1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merriam</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1902</year>
                    <article-title>Triassic Ichthyopterygia from California and
                        Nevada.</article-title>
                    <source>University of California Publications - Bulletin of the Department of
                        Geology</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>63</fpage>
                    <lpage>108</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Wang1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bachmann</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagdorn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuny</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>The Late Triassic black shales of the Guanling area (Ghuizhou
                        Province, Southwest China) – a unique marine reptile and pelagic
                        crinoid fossillagerstätte.</article-title>
                    <source>Palaeontology</source>
                    <volume>51</volume>
                    <fpage>27</fpage>
                    <lpage>61</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Motani3">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Motani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Phylogeny of the Ichthyopterygia.</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology</source>
                    <volume>19</volume>
                    <fpage>473</fpage>
                    <lpage>496</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Maisch2">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maisch</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Cranial osteology of <italic>Guizhouichthyosaurus tangae</italic>
                        (Reptilia: Ichthyosauria) from the Upper Triassic of China.</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology</source>
                    <volume>26</volume>
                    <fpage>588</fpage>
                    <lpage>597</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Shang1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>Q-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>On the occurrence of the ichthyosaur
                            <italic>Shastasaurus</italic> in the Guanling biota (Late Triassic),
                        Guizhou, China.</article-title>
                    <source>Vertebrata Palasiatica</source>
                    <volume>47</volume>
                    <fpage>178</fpage>
                    <lpage>193</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Nicholls2">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholls</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>A new genus of ichthyosaur from the Late Triassic Pardonet
                        Formation of British Columbia: bridging the Triassic Jurassic
                        gap.</article-title>
                    <source>Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences</source>
                    <volume>38</volume>
                    <fpage>983</fpage>
                    <lpage>1002</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Mller1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheyer</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Head</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werneburg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <article-title>Homeotic effects, somitogenesis and the evolution of vertebral
                        numbers in recent and fossil amniotes.</article-title>
                    <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Science, USA</source>
                    <volume>107</volume>
                    <fpage>2118</fpage>
                    <lpage>2123</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Merriam2">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merriam</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1908</year>
                    <article-title>Triassic Ichthyosauria, with special reference to the American
                        forms.</article-title>
                    <source>University of California Memoir</source>
                    <volume>1</volume>
                    <fpage>1</fpage>
                    <lpage>155</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Maisch3">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maisch</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Observations on Triassic ichthyosaurs. Part VI. On the cranial
                        osteology of <italic>Shastasaurus alexandrae</italic> Merriam, 1902 from the
                        Hosselkus Limestone (Carnian, Late Triassic) of Northern California with a
                        revision of the genus.</article-title>
                    <source>Neues Jahrbuch für Geologie und Paläontologie -
                        Abhandlungen</source>
                    <volume>217</volume>
                    <fpage>1</fpage>
                    <lpage>25</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Callaway1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massare</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1989</year>
                    <article-title><italic>Shastasaurus altispinus</italic> (Ichthyosauria,
                        Shastasauridae) from the Upper Triassic of the El Antimonio district,
                        northwestern Sonora, Mexico.</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of Paleontology</source>
                    <volume>63</volume>
                    <fpage>930</fpage>
                    <lpage>939</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-McGowan2">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGowan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title>A new and typically Jurassic ichthyosaur from the Upper Triassic
                        of British Columbia.</article-title>
                    <source>Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences</source>
                    <volume>33</volume>
                    <fpage>24</fpage>
                    <lpage>32</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Merriam3">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merriam</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1895</year>
                    <article-title>On some reptilian remains from the Triassic of Northern
                        California.</article-title>
                    <source>American Journal of Science</source>
                    <volume>50</volume>
                    <fpage>55</fpage>
                    <lpage>57</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-DalSasso1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dal Sasso</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinna</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title><italic>Besanosaurus leptorhynchus</italic> n. gen. n. sp., a new
                        shastasaurid ichthyosaur from the Middle Triassic of Besano (Lombardy, N.
                        Italy).</article-title>
                    <source>Palaeontologia Lombarda Nuova Seria</source>
                    <volume>4</volume>
                    <fpage>1</fpage>
                    <lpage>23</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-DeBeer1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Beer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1971</year>
                    <source>The Development of the Vertebrate Skull</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Clarendon Press.</publisher-name>
                    <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">570</size>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Reisz1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reisz</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sues</surname><given-names>H-D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raath</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Embryos of an Early Jurassic prosauropod dinosaur and their
                        evolutionary significance.</article-title>
                    <source>Science</source>
                    <volume>309</volume>
                    <fpage>761</fpage>
                    <lpage>764</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-McGowan3">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGowan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1974</year>
                    <article-title>A revision of the latipinnate ichthyosaurs of the Lower Jurassic
                        of England (Reptilia: Ichthyosauria).</article-title>
                    <source>Life Science Contributions Royal Ontario Museum</source>
                    <volume>100</volume>
                    <fpage>1</fpage>
                    <lpage>30</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Clarke1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title>Cephalopods in the diets of odontocetes.</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryden</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <source>Research on Dolphins</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Clarendon Press</publisher-name>
                    <fpage>281</fpage>
                    <lpage>321</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Nowak1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <source>Walker's Mammals of the World. Sixth Edition. Volume II</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Baltimore</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>The Johns Hopkins University Press.</publisher-name>
                    <!--===== Restructure page-count as size[@units="page"] =====--><size units="page">1095</size>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Lambert1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Systematics and phylogeny of the fossil beaked whales
                            <italic>Ziphirostrum</italic> du Bas, 1868 and
                            <italic>Choneziphius</italic> Duvernoy, 1851 (Mammalia, Cetacea,
                        Odontoceti), from the Neogene of Antwerp (North Belgium).</article-title>
                    <source>Geodiversitas</source>
                    <volume>27</volume>
                    <fpage>443</fpage>
                    <lpage>497</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Lambert2">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianucci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>A new beaked whale (Odontoceti, Ziphiidae) from the Middle
                        Miocene of Peru.</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology</source>
                    <volume>29</volume>
                    <fpage>910</fpage>
                    <lpage>922</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-MacLeod1">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacLeod</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Review of data on the diets of beaked whales: Evidence of niche
                        segregation and geographic segregation.</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United
                        Kingdom</source>
                    <volume>83</volume>
                    <fpage>651</fpage>
                    <lpage>665</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Massare1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massare</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1987</year>
                    <article-title>Tooth morphology and prey preference of Mesozoic marine
                        reptiles.</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology</source>
                    <volume>7</volume>
                    <fpage>121</fpage>
                    <lpage>137</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Motani4">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Motani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahl</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Large eyeballs in diving ichthyosaurs.</article-title>
                    <source>Nature</source>
                    <volume>402</volume>
                    <fpage>747</fpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Massare2">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massare</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Gastric contents of an ichthyosaur from the Sundance
                        Formation.</article-title>
                    <source>Paludicola</source>
                    <volume>5</volume>
                    <fpage>20</fpage>
                    <lpage>27</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Nicholls3">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholls</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>New material of <italic>Qianichthyosaurus</italic> Li, 1999
                        (Reptilia, Ichtyosauria) from the Late Triassic of southern China, and
                        implications for the distribution of Triassic ichthyosaurs.</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology</source>
                    <volume>22</volume>
                    <fpage>759</fpage>
                    <lpage>765</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Brayard1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brayard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Escarguel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bucher</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monnet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brühwiler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Good genes and good luck: Ammonoid diversity and the end-Permian
                        mass extinction.</article-title>
                    <source>Science</source>
                    <volume>325</volume>
                    <fpage>1118</fpage>
                    <lpage>1121</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Bianucci1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianucci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>A high diversity in fossil beaked whales (Mammalia, Odontoceti,
                        Ziphiidae) recovered by trawling from the sea floor off South
                        Africa.</article-title>
                    <source>Geodiversitas</source>
                    <volume>29</volume>
                    <fpage>561</fpage>
                    <lpage>617</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Motani5">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Motani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Ichthyosauria: evolution and physical constraints of fish-shaped
                        reptiles.</article-title>
                    <source>Annual Review of Earth and Planetary Sciences</source>
                    <volume>33</volume>
                    <fpage>395</fpage>
                    <lpage>420</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Schmitz1">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Storrs</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rieppel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>On a new mixosaurid from the Middle Triassic of
                        Nevada.</article-title>
                    <source>Palaeontographica A</source>
                    <volume>270</volume>
                    <fpage>133</fpage>
                    <lpage>162</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Sander2">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazin</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1993</year>
                    <article-title>The paleobiogeography of Middle Triassic ichthyosaurs: The five
                        major faunas.</article-title>
                    <source>Paleontologia Lombarda, Nuova Serie</source>
                    <volume>2</volume>
                    <fpage>145</fpage>
                    <lpage>152</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Jiang1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Motani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rieppel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>New primitive ichthyosaurian (Reptilia, Diapsida) from the Middle
                        Triassic of Panxian (Guizhou, southwestern China) and its position in the
                        Triassic Biotic Recovery.</article-title>
                    <source>Progress on Natural Science</source>
                    <volume>18</volume>
                    <fpage>1315</fpage>
                    <lpage>1319</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0019480-Motani6">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Motani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>The status of <italic>Himalayasaurus tibetensis</italic>
                        (Ichthyopterygia).</article-title>
                    <source>Paludicola</source>
                    <volume>2</volume>
                    <fpage>174</fpage>
                    <lpage>181</lpage>
                </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    
  </back>
</article>